Student:Hi,everyone.My name is Meghan.
嗨 大家好 我叫Megan
And we were running a really fun study
课后我们会进行一个非常有趣的研究
right after class about mindfulness and vision.
有关内观自省与知见
It shouldn't take more than 10 to 15 minutes.
时间不会超过10到15分钟
So if you are interested,we need more than 60 people.
我们需要至少60个人 所以如果你有兴趣
So just come up to the front after class.
请课后到教室前面来
And it won't take a long time.It's really fun.Thank you.
不会耽搁很久的 真的很有趣 谢谢
(Applause)
掌声
Dr.Tal Ben-Shahar:You know this story about Gertrude Stein.
你们都听过格特鲁德・斯泰因的这个故事
And she was taking philosophy class with William James,
她那时上William James的哲学课
right here in the Art.
就在哈佛拉德克利夫学院
And they had their final exam.And it was spring semester course.
要期末考试了 她上的是春季班
And she comes into the exam.And it's a day like today.
她来到考场 就跟今天一样是个晴朗的日子
And the exam is about metaphysics,and the meaning of life.
考试的内容是形而上学及生命的意义
So she opens the exam and writes,
于是她打开试卷 写道
"Today is too beautiful a day to take an exam."
"多么美好的一天 不应该浪费在考试上"
And she walks out.
然后走出了教室
And you know,as legend has it of course,
而且传说
she gets a straight A in William James' class.
William James的课程她全A通过
Don't use that as an example or an excuse
本学期考试时
later on in this semester.
不要学她 或者拿她当借口
But I really appreciate you being here today.
不过我真的很感谢各位今天出席
It is a beautiful day.
今天天气非常好
I was thinking of having the class outside,
我想过要到户外上课的
but I think - maybe we should.Yeah.
不过…也许我们应该去的 是的
What we are going to do today is finish up on relationships -
今天我们要讲完爱情
we have just a little to go,
还差一点就讲完了
and then start with our final topic for the course,
然后我们会开始讲本课程最后一个话题
which is self-esteem.
也就是自尊
So let me just recap what we did when we discussed relationships.
先回顾一下上回讲到的关于爱情的内容
So we talked about how do we - given our natures,
我们讲到了人类要如何…考虑到人的本性
how do we attain,how do we sustain lasting love,
人类要如何获得 维持长久的爱情与激情
lasting passion when it seems on the physiological level at least
因为从心理学角度看
that our natures are not attuned to that approach.
这似乎有违人的本性
And we talked about - when studying the best relationships,
当我们讲到研究那些最成功的恋情时
the "tip of the stem" - four characteristics,
最成功的恋情有四个特点
based on the work of David Schnarch and John Gottman.
根据David Schnarch和John Gottman的研究发现的
The first one is: relationship is the hard work.
第一条是 经营爱情需要付出努力
It's an illusion to think that
人们往往误以为
the most important thing is finding the right relationship;
寻找合适的爱情对象是最重要的
it is more important to cultivate that one chosen relationship.
其实更重要的是如何经营你选择的爱情
And just like we would not thrive,succeed at work,
就跟工作一样 如果我们找到了梦想中的工作
if we said,"Well,I just found my dream job,"
然后翘起腿 什么也不做
and then put our legs up and relax;
是不可能成功的
similarly we would not thrive in a relationship,
同样的 如果我们在一段恋情中抱有寻找心态
if we have the finding mindset -
我们的恋情也不会成功
we just need to find it and we will live happily ever after,
以为只要找到爱情就能幸福地生活下去
as we talked about movies and where love begins.
我们说过 电影结束时 正是爱情刚开始时
The second component of a healthy,
一段健康长久充满激情的爱情
lasting and passionate relationship related to the first one
第二个组成部分 跟第一个有关联
is the notion of being known rather than being validated,
我们要被了解 而不是被认可
expressing rather than impressing,being open,
表达自己 而不是粉饰自己 坦开心扉
revealing our weaknesses as well as our strengths,our desires,
坦诚自己的弱点 优点 渴望
our passions,our fears and insecurities.
热情 恐惧与不安
And relationships that do,
这样的爱情
or partners that do that within a relationship,
恋爱中的双方如果这样做了
over time attain higher and higher levels of intimacy,happiness,
会渐渐变得更加亲密 更加快乐
and they thrive,and they remain - maintain their passion.
感情更好 激情不哀
That's the second component.
这是第二个组成部分
The third component of a healthy relationship is that
健康爱情的第三个组成部分是
there are conflicts there.
冲突是不可避免的
It is an illusion to believe that
人们往往误以为
the ideal relationship is one that is conflict free
理想的爱情没有冲突
that doesn't exist,
这是不可能的
unless both partners are suppressing serious issues.
除非双方都在刻意躲避严重问题
So there are conflicts in relationships.
所以爱情中时有冲突发生
The challenge is to have more positivity than negativity
当然在一段恋情中 我们的挑战就是要
of course in a relationship,
让积极的大于消极的
but also to learn how to be in the midst of disagreement,
而且要学会如何应对分歧
how to have conflict.
应对冲突
And finally,
最后
the fourth point that we talked about was positive perception;
第四点是积极认知
being a benefit finder,and more than that,
要做优点感知者 不仅如此
being a benefit creator.
还要创造优点
I want to just go back quickly
我快快回顾一遍
and elaborate on something that I didn't last time
然后细讲一些上回没说的东西
about the conflict or conflicts within a relationship.
关于爱情中的冲突
I think the most important essay,
我觉得我读过的
article that I read about relationships in general
关于爱情最重要的文章
was the article on friendship by Ralph Waldo Emerson,
是艾默生的《论友谊》
published in a84a.
发表于1841年
And What Emerson writes about is his ideal friend.
艾默生在其中写了他理想的朋友
Let me quote him.
我来读一段
He says,"in a friend,
他说 "在朋友身上
what I am looking for is not a mush of concessions,
我寻找的不是盲目的让步
a person who would agree with everything that I say;
对我千依百顺的人
rather what I'm looking for is a beautiful enemy,
我寻找的是一个美丽的敌人
a person who will challenge me,who will push me,
能挑战我 敦促我
who will help me in my apprenticeship to the truth."
帮助我寻求真相"
A beautiful enemy - what a beautiful phrase.
美丽的敌人 多美的描述
A conflict free relationship is
没有冲突的爱情
where there are no beautiful enemies.
就没有美丽的敌人
A beautiful enemy is a person who loves us,
美丽的敌人是指因为爱我们
who cares about us enough to challenge us,enough to disagree.
关心我们 所以要跟我们针锋相对的人
And ask yourself what kind of friend,
问问你自己 你想找的
what kind of romantic partner would you like? A yes man or woman?
是什么样的朋友或伴侣 是百依百顺的好好先生或太太吗?
Or a person who would be honest,
还是一个诚恳待人
would have high levels of integrity?
直言规劝的诤友
What is the ideal friend? What is the ideal partner?
理想的朋友 理想的伴侣 是什么样的?
You know it's interesting
有趣的是
this whole idea of beautiful enemy goes way back
美丽敌人这一概念最早可以追溯到
it goes back to the most influential text
西方世界
in certainly the Western world,which is the Bible.
最有影响力的文本 即圣经
In Genesis,God sees that man is alone.
在创世纪中 上帝看到男人独居
So he creates a help meet for him,a woman.A helpmeet.
于是为他造一个配偶帮助他 一个女人 helpmeet
What does that phrase mean? This is the King James translation.
helpmeet这个词是什么意思? 这是钦定版圣经的翻译
Well,if you look at it in the Hebrew,original,
如果你看希伯来原文
"helpmeet" is "ezer kenegdoor",or help as opposition.
"helpmeet"的原文是"ezer kenegdoor" 对立的帮助
In other words,the helpmeet translation,the meet part,M-E-E-T,
也就是说 helpmeet中meet的意思
is like athletic meet,like a competition.
类似运动会的会 也就是竞争
Not helping and they meet together - it's help as opposition.
不是指帮助并取得共识 而是对立的帮助
And already then that it was notices the ideal relationship
所以那时人们已经注意到 理想的爱情
is not one which is all smooth,conflict free;
不是一帆风顺 没有冲突的
it is one where there is some resistance.
而是有阻力的
And it's this resistance that Gottman talked about in the - or
这种阻力就是Gottman曾经谈到…
he is talking about in the 2ast century that it is so important,
本世纪一直谈到的 对于健康的爱情关系
so critical for a healthy relationship,a beautiful enemy,
非常重要且关键的
help as opposition,helpmeet,
一个美丽的敌人 对立的帮助
again with a lot of positivity in the relationship as well.
当然还要有积极的态度
So we move on,and just finish up on positive perception.
我们继续讲积极认知
I want to show you an excerpt from one of my favorite movie
我想给大家放一段视频 是我最爱电影的片段
as I think it's one of the best movies certainly
我认为这部影片是心理学领域
in the realm of psychology ever made,from As Good As it Gets.
最成功的一部影片 《尽善尽美》
And here is the part where Holly Hunter tells Jack Nicholson
这段视频中海伦.亨特告诉杰克.尼克尔森
that he'd better give her a compliment
他最好称赞一下她
and it'd better be a good compliment.
而且要称赞得很好听
Because if it is not,she's getting up and leaving.
否则她就马上离开
He just said something very offensive to her.
他之前刚说了非常冒犯她的话
So here is what he has to say to the woman he loves.
于是他对他爱的女人这么说
[VIDEO: CLIP FROM AS GOOD AS IT GETS]
(视频:电影《尽善尽美》片段)
OK,now I've got a really great compliment for you,and it's true.
好了 现在 我是有些称赞你的话 而且都是真心话
I'm so afraid you're about to say something awful.
我担心你会说出很难听的话
Don't be pessimistic.It's not your style.
悲观可不是你的风格
Okay,here I go: Clearly,a mistake.
好了 我要说了:确实 我错了
I've got this,what - ailment?
我得了 怎么说…小毛病?
My doctor,a shrink that I used to go to all the time,
我的医生 我常去看的心理医生…
he says that in fifty or sixty percent of the cases,
说五到六成的病例…
a pill really helps.
服药就会有效
I hate pills,very dangerous thing,pills.Hate.
我憎恨吃药 药很危险 恨死了
I'm using the word "hate" here,about pills.Hate.
我说药时用的是"恨死了" 恨死了
My compliment is,
我想称赞你的是
that night when you came over and told me that you would never...
那天晚上当你来我家 告诉我你决不会…
All right,well,you were there,you know what you said.
好吧 你当时在场 说过什么你知道
Well,my compliment to you is,
我要恭维你的是…
the next morning,I started taking the pills.
第二天早晨我开始服药
I don't quite get how that's a compliment for me.
这算哪门子的称赞
You make me want to be a better man.
你使我想成为更好的男人
That's maybe the best compliment of my life.
这是我这辈子听过最好听的称赞
Well,maybe I overshot a little,
也许过头了
because I was aiming at just enough to keep you from walking out.
因为我只想着不让你走出去
Dr.Tal Ben-Shahar:This is the essence of benefit creating.
这就是创造优点的本质
You make me want to be a better man,a better woman,
你使我想成为更好的男人 更好的女人
a better person.
一个更好的人
You make me want to do the dishes as well.
你使我想自愿洗餐具做家务
What do we do then? How do we get a relationship
那我们该怎么做?如何让爱情关系或伴侣
or partners in relationships to focus on the positive,
关注积极正面的东西
to focus on the benefit,to focus on creating more good there?
关注优点 创造优点?
Well we are going back to the very first lesson,very first class-
这就得回到第一堂课的内容
and that is the importance of questions.
也就是提问的重要性
Remember,questions begin a quest.
记得 提问是探求的开始
When we ask certain question,
当我们问问题时
we see certain things that we didn't see before.
会留意到以往忽视的东西
When we ask certain question,
我们问问题时
we are also avoiding or not seeing part of reality
也会忽视一些现实情况
remember the geometric shapes.
还记得几何图形吗
It's all you saw - you didn't see colors;
你们只看到了图形 没留意颜色
you didn't see children on the bus;
没看到公车上的孩子
most of you did not see the clock.
大多数人没看到钟
And very often in relationships,
在爱情关系中
the questions that we ask after the honey moon is:
我们在蜜月期之后常问的问题是
"What's wrong? What happened? Or what can be improved?"
"出什么问题了 怎么会这样 怎么改进?"
And again,
重申
these are important questions with very good intentions.
这些问题很重要 出发点是好的
But we just avoid or don't see an important part of reality.
但是我们回避或忽视了一些重要的现实
So the questions that we need to ask
我们需要问的问题
are also the positive questions,
应该是积极的
the questions that will allow us to see the children on the bus.
能让我们看到公车上的孩子的问题
What am I grateful for in my partner?
我的伴侣有哪些优点 让我觉得感激
And it's important to do that always,
经常这么问问自己很重要
especially during difficult times,
尤其是遇到矛盾时
because there's always something to appreciate.
因为总有些东西值得欣赏
And if we don't appreciate that thing,the good depreciates,
如果我们不懂得欣赏 那优点就会贬值
whether it applying to our country,to our organization,
这个道理对我们国家 组织
to our relationship as well as to ourselves.
爱情及自己同样适用
Second positive question:
第二个积极正面的问题是
What is wonderful about our relationships? What's working?
我们的关系有什么美妙之处
Why are we together in the first place?
我们怎么会走到一起的?
What do I love about him,her,us? What's good?
我爱她 他 我们的哪一点?有哪些好的方面?
And when we ask what's good,that's when we perceive it.
我们问"哪些好的方面"时 我们就看到了好的方面
And when we perceive it,when we appreciate it,it appreciates.
当我们看到 欣赏这些好的方面时 它就增值了
It's not a surprise that
我们并不感到惊讶
the statistics are as they are what we saw last time,
上周看到的统计数据显示
that most relationships flounder,
大多数恋情都是苟延残喘
and even those stay together don't really thrive.
即使勉强在一起 也没有什么感情可言
No,it's no coincidence.
这不是巧合
It's because of most of the questions that we asked
这是因为我们问的大多数问题
again,with good intentions.
虽然意图是好的
No one has the intentions certainly
当然了 没人谈恋爱
not going into a relationship to end it or not to thrive in it.
是为了分手 或原地踏步
But most of the questions that we asked,
但是我们问的大多数问题
that we are taught to ask are the ones
我们受到的教育让我们问的问题
that focus on the metaphorical geometric shapes.
都集中在几何图形上
And what we need to do is open up a new quest,no opportunity,
我们要做的是 换一个角度来探索这个问题
see things that are there all along
看到那些一直都在
that we simply have overlooked.
但却被我们忽略了的东西
Again,the quote from Robert M.
引用Robert M.Pirsig
Pirsig,Zen and the Art of Motorcycle Maintenance:
在《万里任禅游》的一句话
so often we look for the truth
我们常常追寻真相
and the truth comes and knocks on our door.
当真相叩响我们的大门时
And we say to it,"Go away! I'm looking for the truth."
我们却说 "走开 我寻求的是真相"
Very often it's right in front of us.
事实上 真相往往就在我们眼前
All we need to do is look.
我们要做的就是仔细看
And one way to look,one way to guide our attention toward
而引导我们注意到
what is right in front of us
眼前的东西的一个方法
is by asking also the positive questions.
就是提出积极正面的问题
OK,so what do we have? What do we have so far?
好了 目前我们讲了哪些
In terms of creating a more positive relationship,
创造积极的爱情关系
in terms of being a benefit creator,
做一个优点创造者
we want to focus on the potential.
我们要关注潜能
And there's one more thing,one more thing that we can do.
还有一件事我们能做到
And that is communicating about positive events.
也就是多沟通积极正面事件
This is taken from the work of Shelly Gable from UCLA
这是加利福尼亚大学的Shelly Gable研究
who's done to my mind the most important work
在我看来 她做了积极心理学领域里
in the area of positive psychology as it relates to relationships
与爱情关系课题有关的最重要的研究
You see there is a lot of research
有很多研究
that has been done on negative communication,
是关于消极沟通的
meaning - what we saw last time - how do you disagree,
什么意思呢 我们上节课讲过如何处理分歧
so rather have a cognitive disagreement
不要把分歧上升到认知层面
rather than an affective or emotional disagreement
不要把分歧恶化为情感上的分裂
focus on the substance,focus on the behavior,
要针对实在的行为
rather than on the person,on the emotions.
而不是针对人和感情
So we know that
我们知道
there's a lot of research on organizational behavior
有很多关于组织行为学
and couples counseling research and so on.
及婚恋咨询的研究
There has been almost no research done
但对情侣间积极沟通的研究
on positive communication between couples,
几乎为零
which is in line with most of the research done in psychology.
这和心理学领域的大多数研究一样
Again,remember,the ratio 21 to 1.
还记得21:1的比率吗
Now it's a little bit less,
现在有所提高了
but around 20 to a ratio,positive to negative research.
大约20:1 积极研究与消极研究的比例
Same when it comes to relationship.
爱情领域也一样
No exception,unfortunately.
很不幸 没有例外
Here comes Shelly Gable and says,
Shelly Gable认为
"We also need to focus on what is working."
"我们还需要关注有用的东西"
And she started to study positive communication
于是她开始研究积极沟通
about positive events quite.
积极事件
And lo and behold,what she found was quite remarkable.
注意 她的发现非常了不起
In fact,what she found was that
她发现
the way couples communicate about positive events
一对伴侣如何沟通积极事件
is a better predictor of long term success in relationships
比起如何沟通消极事件
than how they communicate about negative events.
更能预测到这段感情能否天长地久
When things go well - better predictor of long term,
事情顺利时 比事情不顺时
thriving,passionate relationship than when things do not go well
更可能预测婚恋关系能否长久而甜蜜
So when I come home and tell my partner,
所以我回家告诉我太太
"Oh,I just did this and it was amazing."
"哦 我今天做了这事 太棒了"
Or "I've just seen this and it was breath-taking."
或者"我看了这部电影 太激动人心了"
Or this is what is going on at work.
或者其他工作上的事
This is what's going on in my personal life.
都是我生活中发生的点点滴滴
And it's a good thing.
这是好事
How my partner responds
而我太太如何回应
predicts a long term success of the relationship.
能预测到这段感情能否天长地久
Specifically what Gable is talking about
Gable的意思是指
is active constructive responding.
主动的有建设性的回应
What is active constructive responding?
什么是主动的有建设性的回应?
What she does is divide it into a 2 by 2 C
她分类得出了二行二列的表格
I'm going to present the 2 by 2 now.
我现在就给大家介绍下
This is taken directly from the work of three of my colleagues,
这是直接抄自我三位同僚的著作中
Jane Elsner,Barbara Heilman and Amanda Horn from Australia.
来自澳大利亚的Jane Elsner  Barbara Heilman和Amanda Horn
And here is what they did:
她们是这样进行的
put Shelly Gable's work into an understandable clear 2 by 2.
把Shelly Gable的理论总结成了一张浅显易懂的2x2表
So we have on one dimension constructive
表的横行是有建设性的沟通
versus destructive communication;
与破坏性的沟通
on the other dimension,active versus passive communication.
纵列是主动沟通与被动沟通
Let's go through the four boxes using an example.
我们通过一个例子来说明四个格子
My partner comes home from work and she says,
我太太下班回家 说
"I just got a promotion,
"我升职了
the promotion that I've been waiting for for so long.
这个职位我等了好久
I was just told that I got it."
终于如愿以偿了"
How do I respond? Well,if I'm passive and destructive,
我如何回应? 如果是被动的破坏性的
I show no interest,diverted attention.
我会表现出兴趣缺乏 注意力分散
I say "Mm hmm",and just move on or talk about,
我会说"嗯嗯" 然后讲其他的
"But did you see we got a new flower in the garden?"
"你看到花园里种了新花了吗"
Just talk about something unrelated to it - diverted attention.
说些完全无关的话题 分散注意
This is passive and destructive.Now,destructive and active.
这就是被动的破坏性的回应
Just got promotion.She comes home.
升职后 她回家
And my response is "Oh no,
我回应"哦 不
this means we'll have even less time to spend together!
这样的话我们在一起的时间就更少了
What does this mean about our children now?"
孩子们怎么办?"
Or "what about our holiday that we would go on,
或者"度假的事怎么办?
we were gonna go on next month? It's not possible now,is it?"
说好下个月去的 是不是去不了了?"
Destructive and active.
主动的破坏性的回应
Then there is passive and constructive.
然后是被动的建设性的回应
This is the most common response.
也是最常见的回应
"Oh,that's great.Wonderful.Mm hmm.Wow."
"哦 太好的 太棒了 嗯"
And then there is the forth box,the active and constructive,
然后是第四个框 主动且有建设性的
which is "You just prom... That is amazing!
也就是"你升职了 太好了
Tell me,tell me all about it! So what happened?
告诉我 跟我说说 过程是怎么样的?
Did the boss call you into his office and tell you?
是不是老板叫你去他办公室告诉你的?
How did it happen?" Or "We have to celebrate!"
到底是怎么样的?"或者"我们得好好庆祝庆祝"
Or "let's call our friends and go out!
又或者"打电话叫朋友们出去庆祝
This is amazing! Well done! You've worked so hard for it!
太棒了 干得好 你这么努力
I'm so happy for you!"
我真为感到高兴"
Active constructive.
主动且有建设性
As it turns out,there are consequences,
结果显示 不同的回应
implications to each one of these responses.
会带来不同的影响或后果
Unfortunately,this C the active constructive - not very common.
很可惜 主动且建设性的回应并不常见
Not very common among partners
在情侣之间并不常见
especially after the honey moon phase.
尤其是过了蜜月期后
So when initially the physiological,the novelty,
所以一开始 生理上的新鲜感
the excitement is there,it happens more often.
刺激感强烈 此类回应很常见
But after a while,this goes away,
但一段时间后 就消失了
and with it,as Shelly Gable has shown,
Shelly Gable发现 这种回应一消失
the success of the relationship in a long term.
这段关系就很难长久下去
Now the thing about active constructive responding is that
主动且建设性的回应
it applies to numerous areas in our lives,
适用于我们生活的方方面面
not just to romantic relationships-
不仅是爱情关系
how I communicate with my roommates;
如何与室友沟通
how I communicate with my family,parents,children;
如何与家人 父母 孩子沟通
as a therapist,how I communicate with my clients,
作为心理医生 如何与病人沟通
because again,most of what psychology has been about
因为心理学的初衷
is for the therapists to sit there
就是为了医生坐在这儿
and to be passive constructive - to smile,
被动但有建设性地回应 微笑
"Mm hmm.Wonderful.And then what happened?" -
说 "嗯 不错 然后呢"
As oppose to active constructive and there are consequences.
而不是主动且有建设性地回应 这会引起不良后果
It doesn't mean that
这并不是说
it's the right approach in every relationship every time,
这在任何时候都是最正确的方法
because there are a few constraints here.
因为这种回应方法是有些使用限制的
For example - it has to be win-win events.
比如 必须是双赢事件
Let's say my partner comes from work and says,
比如说我太太下班回家 说
"Tal,you won't believe it.
"Tal 你不会相信的
I just made the most amazing love with my colleague.
我刚和同事疯狂做爱了
He was unbelievable! In fact,I never felt this way before."
他太不可思议了 我从未有过这种感觉"
Now active constructive: Do tell more and what happened then?
主动且有建设的回应:我要知道细节 然后呢
Very difficult to be actively constructive
对大多数人来说 这种情况下
in the situation for most people.
很难做到主动且有建设性
Present company included.Very difficult.So it's about win-win.
包括在座各位 很难 所以这个回应是为了双赢
That's not a win-win as far as I can see.It has to be a win-win.
至少我看来 刚才这个例子不是双赢 必须是双赢
In other words,something that both of us
换句话说 就是要我们双方
or the relationship will benefit from,or at the very least,
恋爱双方都能获益的 或至少
that the other person is not hurt by it.
另一方不会因此受伤害
It has to be genuine.
必须是真诚的
It cannot be fake,because that can't
不能是假的 因为那样…
especially once the partner knows you
尤其是一旦伴侣发现
over time it just doesn't work.
慢慢地就会出现问题
It has to be genuine,
所以必须是真诚的
meaning we have to get into the role of our partner,
我们必须进入伴侣的角色中
identify with,empathize with,
产生认同 共鸣
be one with so that we can genuinely respond to it.
设身处地 这样才能产生真诚的回应
And if we do genuinely respond to it, and if it is a win-win
如果我们能做出真诚的回应 如果这是一个双赢事件
that's when it generates upward spiral on a few levels.
就会带来几个良性循环
First of all: remember,
首先 记得吗
usually when a positive event happens,what happens?
通常当积极事件发生时 会怎么样
There is a spike up and then affective forecasting
会有一个峰值 然后情感预测
Gilbert's work - shows goes back down again.
根据Gilbert的研究 会逐渐回落
What effective constructive responding does
有效的建设性回应
which is "OK,tell me more.
比如"好 再说说
So how was it? Let's celebrate! Give me more details.
当时是怎么样的?我们庆祝吧 告诉我细节
I wanna know! I'm interested!"
我想知道 我很有兴趣"
What it does to the spike is prolong it.
这样的回应会延长峰值
It actually keeps it going for much longer
会使它持续更长的一段时间
than it would have been just a positive event
而不是仅仅一个积极事件那样
and then back to the base level.
很快回落到基本水平
Because we know no matter what promotion we get at work,
因为无论我们获得什么升职
initially it feels great,
一开始感觉很好
no matter what raise initially it feels wonderful,
无论什么情绪上涨 一开始感觉很棒
and then it goes back down again to base level.
然后又会回到基本水平
Active constructive responding actually elongates that raising,
而主动且有建设性的回应会延长
that improvement in well being.
幸福感的提升与增强
So that is one spiral that it creates - feeling better.
所以这是其中一个良性循环 更好的感觉
The second spiral is an inter-personal spiral,
另一种良性循环 是人际关系的
meaning a person who actively constructively responds genuinely
也就是说作出真诚主动有建设性回应的人
enters the same upward spiral,
会获得相同的良性循环
meaning people
也就是说
who do that genuinely become happier as a result of
真诚回应的人会变得更快乐
because they experience the event.
因为他们也经历了这一事件
And they themselves benefit and become happier,
他们自己也从中获益 变得更快乐
again a win-win potentially.
所以又是一种双赢
And finally,it also does what positive psychology
最后一点 它和积极心理学的整体作用一样
as a whole does which is build positive capacity.
累积积极正面情绪
Remember positive psychology
记得吗 积极心理学
takes us not just from the zero to the positive,
不仅让我们从0变得积极
it also helps us better deal with the negative to the zero.
还帮助我们更好地把消极变为0
Partners who actively constructive respond to one another
作出主动且有建设性回应的伴侣
are building capacity for hard times.
是在为艰难时刻累积积极正面情绪
In fact one of the most interesting research that
事实上 很久以前
were done long time ago was that couples
有一项有趣的实验
when things went well or they were - wasn't,
当生活顺利时 夫妻双方…
that language wasn't used - but essentially
虽然当时的研究没有用这样的术语 但意思上是相同的
when they actively constructively responded to one another
1920年代 夫妻双方能主动
and supported one another back in the 1920s,
且有建设性地回应对方 支持对方
once the Great Depression hit,
大萧条发生时
the relationship actually became better;
他们的婚姻反而变得更坚固了
whereas partners who didn't have a good before,
而没有做到这点的伴侣
the relationship very often dissolved,became worse.
他们的婚姻往往会瓦解 变糟
In other words,when they built the capacity,
换句话说 他们累积正面情绪
it helped them also deal with the hard times
应对困难时期
such as 1929 and the 1930s.
比如20年代 30年代
There are no short cuts when it comes to good relationships,
幸福的爱情 健康的爱情
to healthy relationships.
没有捷径
It is hard work,if you want to succeed,
如果你想要成功 就需要努力
just like it is in every other domain in life.
跟生活的其他领域一样
There are no short cuts.
没有捷径可走
However,that doesn't mean that hard work cannot be enjoyable,
但是 这不是说 努力就是痛苦的
cannot be pleasurable as well as meaningful.
它可以意义非凡且充满乐趣
And when that hard work is pleasurable and meaningful,
当你的努力是充满乐趣 意义非凡时
over time that leads to a happier relationship,
渐渐地 就会使爱情更幸福
happier individuals to a win-win togetherness.
使你们更快乐 建立双赢的伴侣关系
I want to end but just addressing a point that
结束这部分前 我还想说一点
many of you have raised with me:
你们很多人都问过我
and that is should we even talk about relationships
当我们讲追求幸福时
in the context of pursuit of happiness.
我们应该讲恋情吗?
And the answer for most people is yes with some discomfort.
大多数人的回答是 应该 但有所保留
Yes,because it is the No.1 generator of the ultimate currency;
说"是"的原因是 爱情是幸福的最重要来源
some discomfort
有所保留的原因是
because pursuing happiness is by its nature selfish.
追求幸福的本质是自私的
I mean actually when I am thinking about my happiness,
我的意思是 我思考我的幸福时
I'm thinking by definition about the self.
毫无疑问 我想的是自己
And shouldn't relationship be about the opposite of selfishness,
难道恋情不是与自私对立的吗
in other words,about altruism.
换句话说 恋情是利他主义的
So let me just say a few words about this.
关于这点我有几句话要说
Let's take an example from teaching.
就拿教书作为例子
Imagine this: imagine that I actually don't like teaching.
想象一下 假如我不喜欢教书
I don't like to teach.
我不喜欢教书
I don't like coming here on Tuesdays and Thursdays.
不喜欢每周二周四来这里
And in fact it's very painful for me.
对我来说非常痛苦
However,I have a deep sense of duty because of my upbringing,
但是 出于我受到的教育 我学的哲理
because of the philosophies that I read.
我有很强的责任感
I have a deep sense of duty to other people.
我对别人有很强的责任感
And I know that positive psychology is
我知道积极心理学
or has some important messages to give people.
给教给别人一些很重要的知识
And therefore I teach it,not because I like it,
于是我来上课 不是因为我喜欢教书
but because I think it can potentially help other people.
而是因为我认为它能帮助到别人
And I wake up in Tuesdays and Thursdays mornings,
我每周二周四早上醒来
and I dread going to class.
痛苦地来到教室
The hour and a half seems like eternity to me.
一个半小时的课让我度日如年
The last thing in the world that I want to do is teach,
我最不想做的事就是教书
but I'm driven by my sense of duty,because I'm an altruist,
但是我的责任感驱使我这样 因为我是利他主义者
I'm sacrificing myself for what I think is a greater good.
我为伟大的事业牺牲自己
Now think of the alternative.
再想想另一种情况
Imagine this teacher and then imagine the alternative.
想象与刚才那位老师相反的情况
And the alternative is me.
就是我
I love teaching.
我爱教书
There is no where else I would rather be right now than here.
我最喜欢的地方就是教室的讲台
I love positive psychology.
我爱积极心理学
I can't wait to get onto my computer and write the lectures;
我等不及要打开电脑备课
I can't wait to prepare the powerpoints
等不及准备幻灯片
and work hard on Google image to do so;
搜索Google图片
I can't hardly wait to interact with you.
我等不及要与你们互动
I love being here every Tuesday and Thursday.
我喜欢每周二周四站在这里
It is my passion,it is my calling,
这是我热爱的 我的使命
it is both pleasurable and meaningful to me
和你们在一起上课 对我来说
to spend time with you.
意义非凡又充满乐趣
And now I ask you which teacher would you rather have?
那么你们想要哪一位老师
The teacher who is here out of a sense of duty,
是出于责任和利他主义动机
for altruistic reasons?
才来上课的老师
Or is the person who is here for selfish reasons,
还是那个为了满足自己
because he would rather be here more than any other place?
喜欢上课这个爱好而来上课的老师?
I also ask you
另一个问题
which teacher do you think would be a better teacher?
你觉得哪个老师会是更好的老师
And now I ask you,which partner would you rather have,
引申开去 你们会想要怎样的伴侣
a partner who is with you just because they feel like
一个跟你在一起是因为他们觉得
"Well,that person really needs me,"
"这人很需要我"
or "I feel sorry for the person,"
"这家伙真可怜"
"I don't really like that person,but I'm there
"我不是真的喜欢他
just to be there for them,because,out of a sense of duty"?
我只是出于责任感 支持他"的人?
Or would you rather have a person who is with you
还是跟你在一起是因为
because you are the most important person in their lives,
你是他们生命中最重要的人
because they care about so much that the I becomes the We?
因为他们如此关心你 从"我"变成了"我们"?
They care about you as much as they care about themselves.
他们像关心自己一样 关心你
They include you in their circle of the self.
把你纳入了自己的一部分
Which relationship do you think will thrive more?
你们认为哪种爱情会成功?
Now that does not mean that
这不是说
there is no sacrificing in relationships;
爱情中不会有牺牲
that does not mean that if my partner is unwell,
也不是说 如果我伴侣身体不适
or needs my help,I would not go out of my way,
或者需要我帮助 我不会全力以赴
even if it means giving up something that
即使那意味着需要放弃
I really really want to do at that point.
我当时的梦想
Of course,in healthy relationships,
当然了 在健康的恋情中
when the Is become a We,sacrifices exist,
当我变成了我们 就会有牺牲
and there is healthy sacrifice.
但这是健康的牺牲
But it's not a relationship that
这样的恋情
is based fundamentally on the sense of duty
它的基础不是责任感
or altruistic negation of the self.
不是否定自我的利他主义
As Nathaniel Branden says,the more independent we are,
Nathaniel Branden说过 我们越独立
the more inter-dependent we can become.
就越互相依赖
That's when the I becomes a We.
当我变成我们时 就会这样
Again this is something which goes against much of our teachings
这与我们所讲过的内容相反
it's not always easy to accept,but again
不是很容易接受
this class much more than it is about positive psychology,
但是这门课不仅是关于积极心理学
is about reality psychology.
还有现实心理学
And ask yourself what partner would you rather be,
问问你自己 想成为哪种伴侣
what partner would you rather have,
想拥有哪种伴侣
what teacher would you rather have - completely analogous.
想要哪种老师 举一反三
OK.Let's move on now to the very last topic of this class.
好了 我们来讲本课程最后一个话题
As I've said many times,I never procrastinate;
我说过很多次 我从不拖延
I just use Google image.
直接用了Google图片
I started to think explicitly about the topic about self-esteem
当我还在哈佛这里读本科大四时
when I was a senior,as an undergraduate here.
就开始非常认真地思考自尊这个话题
I started to think about it when I noticed another phenomenon.
当时我注意到一个现象
So that was after I switched into philosophy and psychology.
那是我转专业到哲学和心理学后
I was very happy on my concentration.
我对自己的学业很满意
I was very happy playing in the squash team.
在壁球队里也很开心
Harvard was going great for me.
哈佛生活对我来说一帆风顺
But then I started to notice something that was unclear,
但后来我发现一些很费解
didn't make sense to me.
无法理解的事情
And that was the fact that I had low self-esteem
我自尊程度相当低
or so it seemed at least.
至少看起来是这样
And it didn't make sense to me,
我无法理解
because I was doing well,I had won prizes,
因为我表现不错 得过奖
I had received a lot of accolades,a lot of support,
屡获表扬 支持
whether it's from my roommates,friends,family,
有来自室友的 朋友的 家人的
lot of pads on the back in athletics,in academics.
运动还是学术都屡获嘉奖
And yet I had low self-esteem.
但我的自尊还是很低
And it just didn't make any sense to me.
这让我很不解
There was another thing that baffled me even more.
还有一件事更让我困惑
It was as if on some level I was punished by success.
在某种程度上 我觉得我的成功在惩罚我
What do I mean by that?
这是什么意思?
Every time when I would succeed,or when I did get praise,
每次我获得成功 或者被表扬
my self-esteem would increase,would improve.
我的自尊就会增加 改进
But then very quickly afterwards,
但很快
it went down,back to its base level and even lower.
又回到了基础水平 甚至更低
And in order to raise it back up again,
为了重新提升它
I needed even more praise,
我就需要更多表扬
even more accolades than I needed before.
比以前更多的赞赏
And the metaphor that kept coming to mind
有一个比喻不断出现在我脑海里
was Sisyphus pushing a rock up on mountain.
科林斯王推石头上山的故事
I would push the rock up the mountain,
我就好像在推石头上山
struggle till the next victory came.
挣扎奋斗直到获得成功
And the next victory came and I got the praise,
成功后我得到表扬
I got the accolades,I got the prize.
获得赞赏 奖品
And my self-esteem was high.
我的自尊提升了
I was on top of the mountain.
我处在了山顶
And then this rock would be rolled down again.
然后石头又滚了下来
And I would have to run down and start to push it up again
我不得不跑下山重新再推
only this time,the hill was even steeper;
而且这次 山坡更陡峭了
I would have to struggle even more and I would get up there again
我不得不更加努力 才能到达山顶
and then it would roll back down.
然后石头又滚下山
Now it wasn't enough to have the accolade,the praise,the amount
以前那些赞赏 表扬
the quality and the quantity that I had before.
已经不够了
I needed even more just to get onto the same mountain,
我需要更多才能重新回到山顶
even steeper,even more difficult.
更陡峭 更困难
And it didn't make sense to me.
我想不通
And then I took a class - senior year
到了大四 我选修了一门课
ended up being one of my favorite classes for various reasons
出于诸多原因 那成为了我最爱的课程之一
which I will not go into now,Fairy Tales.
童话课 原因我现在不想细讲
I took Fairy Tales and we read Emile, Rousseau's Emile
我选修了童话课 我们读了卢梭的《爱弥儿》
And Maria Tatar talked about wonderful theories and it clicked.
Maria Tatar讲到了很多精彩的理论 我想通了
I ended up writing my senior thesis,
于是我的毕业论文
my final paper for that class on self-esteem
那门课的期末论文写的就是自尊
and that eventually became my dissertation.
最终发展成了我的学位论文
That's actually what I wrote my PHD on,this topic.
我的博士论文写的就是这个话题
So what I want to do today is show with you some of the insights
所以今天我想和大家分享
that I got in Fairy Tales as well as other thinkers
我在童话课上的感悟及其他思想家
who have been thinking about this topic of self-esteem,
对于自尊话题的思考
because it is important.
因为这非常重要
It is not for nothing that
我以自尊的话题结束这门课程
I end the course with the topic of self-esteem,
不是毫无缘由的
because it is at the foundation,
因为它是基础
at the core of so many of the other things that we discussed,
是我们之前讲过的很多内容的核心
whether it's healthy relationships,
无论是健康的婚恋关系
whether it's happiness in general,
还是快乐
whether it's benefit finding or benefit creating,
无论是寻找优点 还是创造优点
whether it's being known rather than validated.
无论是被了解 还是被认可
Self-esteem encompasses so many of these ideas.
自尊涉及方方面面的内容
So here is what we are gonna do.
我们要讲以下内容
First of all,we are going to talk about why is it important?
首先 为什么自尊非常重要
A lot of misunderstanding about what self-esteem is and is not.
对于自尊的种种误解
We are going to talk about some theories
可以运用到生活中的
that can apply to our lives.
一些理论
And then we'll elaborate on the paradox that I just talked about,
然后我们会细讲我刚才提到的矛盾
that sometimes success actually
有时候成功
leads to lower levels of self-esteem.
会降低自尊
And why does that happen? We'll explain that.And
为什么会这样 我们到时会解释
then I'll introduce essentially my dissertation on self-esteem,
然后我会介绍我关于自尊的学位论文
where I divided the one construct into three distinct components,
我把它分为三个清晰的部分
which are dependence self-esteem
依赖性自尊
self-esteem that is generated by others' praise or approval;
即由他人表扬和认同而产生的自尊
independence self-esteem - self-esteem that comes from within,
独立自尊 即内在产生的自尊
self-esteem that is not contingent
这种自尊不取决于
on what other people say,self generated;
别人的评价 是自我生成的
and finally,unconditional self-esteem,or a state of being,
最后 无条件的自尊 也可以称作一种自然状态
where we simply and naturally exist.
我们自然的存在感
So I'll talk about these three levels
我会讲到这三个层面的自尊
and how we can cultivate independent
以及如何培养独立自尊
as well as unconditional self-esteem.
及无条件自尊
And finally we will end by next time by talking about
最后 下节课我们会讲到
how we can enhance our levels of self-esteem.
如何提高自尊水平
Now many people when they listen to a lecture on self-esteem,
很多人参加自尊讲座后
go into evaluation mode and say,
会进行自我评估 认为
"OK,so do I have high self-esteem?" - I meaning you;
"好了 我的自尊高吗?" 我说的"我"是说你们
or "Is my self-esteem higher than the person sitting next to me,
或者"我的自尊比旁边那人高吗?
or my partner or friend?"
比我伴侣或朋友高吗?"
And the answer to this question is you can't really know,
回答是 你无法得知
meaning we can't measure self-esteem "objectively".
因为我们无法客观地衡量自尊
We don't really where it is in the brain yet
我们还不知道它处在我们大脑哪个部位
we may be able to 10 years from now,20 years from now.
也许10年20年后可以
But that's not an important question,just like "Am I happy?"
但这个问题不重要 就像"我快乐吗"一样
or not is not an important question,
也不是个重要问题
in fact a misleading question.
它其实是一个误导人的问题
The question rather,remember,is "How can I become happier?"
记住 你要问的应该是"如何才能变得更快乐?"
The same with self-esteem
自尊也是如此
the question is not "Do I have high or low self-esteem?"
你要问的不是"我的自尊是高是低"
but rather "How can I enhance my self-esteem?"
而是"如何才能提高自尊"
Because as I argue shortly,there cannot be too much self-esteem.
因为我等一下会讲到 自尊越高越好
But sometimes people associate too much self-esteem to arrogance,
但有时候人们把自尊与自大
conceit and narcissism.
自负 自恋过多地联系在一起
It's not self-esteem.
这些不是自尊
In fact it is the exact opposite of it; it's lack thereof.
恰恰相反 是缺乏自尊
So having stronger sense of self is a good thing.
所以强烈的自我感是件好事
And the question is "How can I enhance it?"
问题是"如何提升它?"
Today my self-esteem is higher than it was
今天 我的自尊比15年前
when I started thinking about it 15 years ago.
我刚考虑这个问题时提升了很多
And hopefully 15 years or 5 years from now
希望5或15年后
it will be higher than it is today.
会比今天还要高
It is a life-long process.
这是个终身的过程
And we'll talk about how that life-long process unfolds
我们会谈这个终身过程是如何展开的
and what we can do to expedite it,to intensify it.
如何才能加快 加强这一过程
So first of all: definition of the self-esteem.
首先 自尊的定义
There are numerous definitions.
自尊有多种定义
Let me read you just a few from the main thinkers in the area.
我读几条重要思想家对此的认识
So Albert Bandura,Stanford Professor,
斯坦福大学教授Albert Bandura
explains gate to self-esteem,
解释了通向自尊的大门
quote in terms of how people evaluate themselves:
说到人们是如何评估自我的 他是这样说的
"Those who express the sense of unworthiness
"那些认为自己没有价值的人
are said to have low self-esteem,
会被视为自尊较低
or the person who is to express self-pride
那些表现出自傲的人
are said to hold themselves in highest esteem."
会被视为自尊极高"
Another well-known thinker in the area,
这一领域另一位著名思想家
Germain defines self-esteem as
Germain认为自尊是
"the judgment and feelings about the self." -
"对于自我的评判与感受"
Very simply: the judgment and feelings about the self.
非常简单 对于自我的评判与感受
Coopersmith,one of the most important thinkers in the area:
Coopersmith 该领域最重要的思想家之一
"Self-esteem is an evaluation which individual makes
"自尊是个体作出的
and customarily maintains with regard to himself.
并经常保持的对自己的评价
It expresses an attitude of approval or disapproval
表达了一种对自己赞许或不赞许的态度
and indicates the extent to which individual believes himself
标志了个体对自己能力 身份
to be capable,significant,successful and worthy."
成就及价值的信心"
Capable,significant,successful and worthy.
能力 身份 成就 价值
"In short,self-esteem is a personal judgment of worthiness that
"简而言之 自尊是对自我价值的评判
is expressed in the attitudes individual holds toward himself."
通过个人对于自我的态度表现出来"
It's about the attitude that I have toward myself.
所以自尊说的是我对自己的态度
It's the evaluative part of the self concept.
是对自我概念的评估
The definition that I will use that I used in my dissertation
我对自尊作出的定义 在我的论文里也用过这个定义
and I think it captures the best what self-esteem is about
我认为这个定义最成功地道出了自尊的本质
is Nathaniel Branden's.
是Nathaniel Branden的理论
Nathaniel Branden,
Nathaniel Branden
considered by many to be the father of the self-esteem movement
被很多人称为美国乃至全世界的
in this country if not the world,
自尊运动的先驱
a therapist and philosopher that
身为心理医生及哲学家
has been working in the area for 50 years,
他在这一领域研究了50年
defines self-esteem as following:
他对自尊做出了如下定义
"the disposition to experience oneself
"一种觉得自己
as competent to cope with the basic challenges of life
能够应付生活中的基本挑战
and as worthy of happiness."
值得享受快乐的感觉"
Two components - the feeling,the experience of competence
两个组成部分 能力感
and the feeling and experience of worthiness.
价值感
Both are important.
两者都很重要
If we lack one,we very often have low self-esteem.
缺少任何一个 自尊就会很低
Personal example: I felt very competent at what I was doing,
个人体会: 我觉得自己能胜任手头的工作
whether it was on the squash court,
无论是在壁球场上
whether it was in relationships,
还是婚恋关系中
whether it was academically,and yet my self-esteem was low,
还是学术领域 但是我的自尊仍旧很低
because I didn't have the worthiness component
因为我缺少自尊的
now I know of self-esteem.
价值感这个组成部分
So one or the other are not enough - we need both.
所以光有一个是不够的 要两者兼备
Nathaniel Branden continues:
Nathaniel Branden继续说
"Of all the judgments we pass in our lives,
"我们在生活中作出的所有判断
none is as important as the one we pass on ourselves."
没有哪个比对自己作出的判断更重要了"
Why? Because we are constantly with ourselves.
为什么 因为我们时刻有自我意识
It affects every area of our lives when we are alone,
它影响我们生活的各个领域 我们孤身一人时
when we are with others,when we are at work,when we are doing,
与别人在一起时 工作时
when we are working by ourselves,when we are in a team.
独自工作时 与人合作时
As Goethe said,"The greatest evil that can befall man is that
歌德说过"降临于人最大的邪恶是
he should come to think ill of himself."
让他否认自己"
So high self-esteem is important or self-esteem is
所以高自尊非常重要 或者说
the sense of self is important.
自我感很重要
And yet,if we look around us,
但是如果我们环顾四周
if we look within us,there's much room for improvement.
反省自身 会发现还有很多改进空间
Some people more than others,
有些人多 有些人少
but for everyone,there's room for improvement.
但每个人都有一定的改进空间
Here are some of the benefits associated with high self-esteem.
以下是高自尊的一些益处
First of all,mental health.
首先 心理健康
High levels of resilience,dealing with difficulties
心理抵抗能力和应付困难的能力加强
this applies to kids who are 6 years old,or to 96 year olds.
从6岁孩童到96岁老人都是这样
Throughout our lives,the higher levels of self-esteem,
纵观一生 自尊程度越高
the more resilient we are,
心理抵抗能力越强
the better we are able to deal with anxiety,with depression,
能更好地应对焦虑 抑郁
with inevitable hardships that arise.
各种无法避免的困境
Relationships improve.
改善人际关系
This applies very much
这点非常适用于
as we'll see later to romantic relationships;
婚恋关系 我们稍后会讲到
it applies as much to friendships;
同样适用于友谊
it applies as much to family relationships.
和家庭关系
In the words of Branden: Self concept is destiny.
Branden说 自我概念就是命运
Beliefs or self-fulfilling prophecy
信念或自我实现预言
if I think of myself,believe in myself,believe that I'm worthy,
如果我相信自己 相信自己值得快乐
that I'm capable of a lot,
相信自己有能力
I will,I'm much more likely to succeed.
那么我成功的可能性更大
Remember the two predictors John Carlton
还记得John Carlton提出的
had for highly successful HBS grads:
哈佛商学院研究生成功的两个因素吗
the first one was that they were always asking questions,
第一条是他们总是问问题
always wanting to learn more.
总是想学习更多
The second was they believed in themselves.
第二条是他们相信自己
This was what distinguished,the most successful from the rest.
这使他们在其他成功者中脱颖而出
Self concept is destiny.
自我概念即命运
Emotional intelligence,a concept popularized by Daniel Goleman,
Daniel Goleman普及的情商概念
initially introduced by Salovey from Yale,
最早是由耶鲁大学的Salovey
by Gartner from Harvard.
和哈佛大学的Gartner提出的
How affective we are with others,
我们对他人的情感
our inter-personal intelligence together
我们的人际智能 这些合起来
making emotional intelligence
使得自尊高的人
much higher for people with high levels of self-esteem.
情商高很多
And finally,the subtotal happiness.
最后 快乐
In my research as well as other people's research,
无论是我的研究 还是其他人的研究
the correlation between self-esteem and happiness is above .6 C
自尊与快乐的相关系数都超过0.6
very high correlation,not the only determinant,
这一数字相当高 虽然它不是快乐唯一的决定因素
but certainly one of the major determinants of happiness.
但绝对是主要决定因素之一
On the other hand,low self-esteem is associated with anxiety.
另一方面 低自尊常常与焦虑并存
I'm not talking about the natural kind of anxiety.
我说的不是自然的焦虑
If I'm standing on the cliff,
如果我站在悬崖边
and I feel some anxiety looking down,that's natural.
往下看时感到焦虑 这很自然
That's healthy.
这是健康的
Permission to be human - it's important to experience anxiety.
人的天性 经历这种焦虑很重要
It's natural.
这很自然
We all do it,just like the law of gravity.
人人都会感受到 就像万有引力定律
It's part of our physical nature.
是我们的生理天性之一
Anxiety is part of human nature.
焦虑是人的天性之一
But anxiety that is unhealthy
不健康的焦虑
is one that is for no apparent reason.
是指毫无缘由的焦虑
Again,Branden calls it self-esteem anxiety.
Branden称之为自尊焦虑
Suddenly waking up in the middle of night
半夜突然醒来
and feeling anxiety for no apparent reason,
感到毫无缘由的焦虑
or going through life generally with a sense of anx or fear,
或者日常生活中经常感到一种焦虑感或恐惧感
not really clear,not really sure of what.
却不明白是为了什么
That is very often the symptom of low self-esteem.Depression.
这通常是低自尊的症状 抑郁
Again we are constantly spending time with ourselves.
我们时刻有自我意识
We are constantly inside of our minds -
我们时刻关注自己的脑袋
the I is constantly evaluating the me.
我时常在评估自己
And if the evaluation is wanting,
如果评估显示不够格
if it's low,very often it leads to depression.
如果评估很低 通常会导致抑郁
Psychosomatic symptoms include insomnia,include getting sick,
身心失调症状包括失眠 患病
because our immune system is lower -
因为我们的免疫系统变得脆弱
physical immune system is lower and so on.
生理免疫系统变得脆弱
Self concept is destiny.
自我概念即命运
It applies to our top performance;
它是我们取得最高效率的原因
it applies to our worst performance as well.
也是我们取得最差表现的原因
School children who are under achievers very often -
成绩差的学生通常…
that's associated or the result of low self-esteem.
自尊较低
Nathaniel Branden calls self-esteem
Nathaniel Branden把自尊称为
"the immune system of consciousness".
"意识的免疫系统"
The immune system of consciousness
意识的免疫系统
when we have high self-esteem,
我们自尊较高时
it means we are more resilient psychologically.
心理抵抗能力更强
Remember,a strong immune system does not mean we don't get sick.
记住 强健的免疫系统并不意味着不会生病
It means we get sick but less often;
而是较少得病
and when we do get sick,we recover more promptly.
如果生病了 能更迅速地恢复
The immune system of consciousness.
意识的免疫系统
It means that sickness is the exception; well being is the rule.
强健的意识疫系统 意味着我们常快乐少生病
It means that we are pursuing happiness,
意味着我们追求快乐
rather than constantly running away from unhappiness.
而不是躲避不快乐
These are all signs of high self-esteem versus low self-esteem
这些是高自尊与低自尊的区别
resilient psychology.
心理抵抗能力
Bednar and Peterson,
Bednar与Peterson
two researchers in the area asked the question,
该领域两位研究者提出了一个问题
"What is the underlying cause,or is there an underlying cause
"大多数心理问题或精神病
to most psychological disorders and ailments?"
根本病因是什么 或者说有没有根本病因?"
And what they came up with was one construct,
他们提出了一个构想
and that was self-esteem.
即自尊
Self-esteem is critical.
自尊至关重要
First of all in understanding,
首先 在理解层面
in understanding many of the emotional and behavioral problems;
理解各种情绪及行为问题
and second,in terms of most,not all,but most of the emotional
其次 治疗大多数 并不是所有
and behavioral problems - self-esteem at the core.
情绪及行为问题 自尊都是核心
Finally it doesn't just apply on the individual level,
最后 它不仅适用于个人
it also applies on the societal level.
还适用于社会层面
It was California Task Force by the government
政府成立的加州健康专责小组
that coined self-esteem as a social vaccine,
将自尊称为社会疫苗
because what they found was self-esteem was associated,
因为他们发现自尊与…
low self-esteem was associated with substance abuse,
低自尊与药物滥用
teen pregnancy,school drop-out rates,violence and crime.
未成年怀孕 辍学 暴力及犯罪有关
And high self-esteem: that the opposite
而高自尊恰恰相反
help overcome these social ailments.
能帮助克服这些社会顽疾
Again,not a panacea,but helps in many ways.
虽然不是万灵药 但在各个方面起到了积极作用
So self-esteem is good.
所以自尊是好的
Self-esteem in fact is great,is important.
非常重要
However not all is rosy in self-esteem land.
但在研究自尊这个领域里 不是所有人都意见一致的
And there are some criticisms,
有一些反对的声音
some criticisms by very important thinkers in the area.
有些甚至是该领域重要的思想家提出的
One of them,the leading one is Roy Baumeister form Florida,
其中之一是 佛罗里达州的Roy Baumeister提出的
equating self-esteem with arrogance and conceit.
他将自尊等同于自大自负
Because if you are taking a questionnaire and,of narcissism,
因为如果你进行关于自恋的问卷调查
those who are high on narcissism
会发现自恋程度高的人
will also score very high on a self-esteem measure.
自尊分也非常高
But here lies the problem.
但问题在这里
And here in the paper you are reading
你们阅读的论文
is how we can debunk at least this criticism - there are others.
至少可以反驳这种批评 当然还有其他的
You see,a person who is a narcissist,
如果一个人自恋自大
who is arrogant,doesn't have high self-esteem.
自尊程度其实不高
I mean we all know that's common sense.
这是常识
Someone who walks into a room immediately looking like a peacock,
一个像高傲的孔雀一样走进教室
showing off,bragging
摆现炫耀
does that person have high self-esteem? Probably not.
这人一定是高自尊吗 不一定
A person who is humble,who doesn't need constantly show off
一个谦虚不摆现的人
is usually the person with higher levels of self-esteem.
往往自尊程度更高
As Rollo May,
正如Rolly May
one of the founders of humanistic psychology movement says,
人本主义心理学运动创始人说过
"The person who feels weak becomes a bully,
"软弱的人变成恶霸
the inferior person a braggart;
自卑的人变成吹牛大王
a flexing of muscles,much talk,cockiness,
炫耀武力 夸夸其谈 骄傲自大
an endeavor to brazen it out,
厚颜无耻
are symptoms of covert anxiety in a person or a group."
都是个人或集体隐匿的焦虑症状
It's the exact opposite of self-esteem.
这与自尊恰恰相反
Unfortunately today our measures of self-esteem
可惜 如今我们评估自尊的方法
are through questionnaires.
都是通过问卷调查进行
And if you ask a narcissist,"Do you have high self-esteem",
如果你问一个自恋者 "你自尊高吗"
the answer will of course be yes.
回答当然是 是
However,the questionnaires are not so,
但是当今大多数
most of the questionnaires are not sophisticated enough today
问卷调查还没有复杂到
to differentiate between true self-esteem
足以区分真自尊
and what Nathaniel Branden calls,pseudo self-esteem,
和Nathaniel Branden所说的伪自尊
the pretense of self-efficacy and self-respect.
自我效能与自尊心的伪装
Soon we'll be able to measure that much more objectively.
不久的将来我们将能更客观的衡量它们
So that's for narcissism.But there are other criticisms.
这是把自尊等同自恋的批评 但是还有其他批评
And that is that self-esteem,
其中一个认为 自尊
high self-esteem leads to unrealistic evaluation
高自尊会使人过分高估自己
and that ultimately hurts people.
最终对人造成伤害
Let me read you something from Times magazine
我来读一段时代周刊的报道
a report about a certain test that was given to kids 13 year olds
这篇报道是讲全世界各国13岁孩子
in different countries around the world.
进行的一次测验
A standardized math test was given to 13 year olds
去年 6个国家的13岁孩子
in 6 countries last year.
做了一次标准化数学测验
Koreans did the best;
韩国孩子表现最好
Americans did the worst,coming behind Spain,Ireland,and Canada
美国孩子表现最差 排在西班牙 芬兰 加拿大之后
Now the bad news: besides being shown triangles and equations,
坏消息是  除了三角与等式外
the kids were shown the statement "I'm good at mathematics."
试卷上还有一道判断题"我擅长数学"
Americans were No.1 with an impressive 68 percent in agreement.
美国孩子居然有68%选"是" 排在第一
American students may not know their math
美国孩子可能不懂数学
but they have evidently absorbed the lessons
但显然他们对新式的自尊课程
of the newly fashionable self-esteem curriculum,
掌握的非常好
wherein kids are taught to feel good about themselves.
这些课程教会孩子们自我感觉良好
Wherein kids are taught to feel good about themselves
and I will add "no matter what".
我还要再加句"无论做什么"
Because teachers,many teachers have learned
因为很多老师
to just give indiscriminant praise - why?
不分青红皂白地给予赞美 为什么?
Because self-esteem is good,it's a social vaccine
因为自尊是好的 是社会疫苗
and there's a lot of research to back that up.
有很多研究支持这一点
And how do you enhance self-esteem? -
那如何提高自尊呢
By showering people with "Oh,you are terrific!
要不停跟他们说"哦 你真厉害
You are wonderful! You are great!"
你太棒了 你真行"
But that,it turns out does not help these students.
但结果显示 这对学生们并没有帮助
In fact,in the long run - in the short term,it feels good,
事实上 长期来看…短期内感觉良好
but in the long term it actually reduces their motivation to work
但长期来看反而降低了他们的学习动力
it makes them unrealistic;
让他们变得不切实际
and in the long run,
长期来看
it makes them less happy than they potentially could have been.
反而减低了他们本来可能获得的快乐
In fact,it boomerangs.
产生了反效果
Again with good intentions
所以 意图是好的
because they want to raise their self-esteem.
因为老师们想提高学生的自尊
So how do we salvage self-esteem's self-esteem?
那如何拯救自尊呢?
By understanding its true nature.
需要先理解它的真实性质
First of all,self-esteem is not a product of empty reinforcement
首先 自尊不是空洞的心理强化能够产生的
Oh you are wonderful;you are terrific;
哦 你真棒 你好厉害
you are great - no matter what.
你真行 不管是不是都赞扬
That hurts self-esteem in the long term.
长期来看还会损害自尊
Self-esteem has to be distinguished from pseudo self-esteem
自尊必须与伪自尊区分开
once again the pretense of self-efficacy
也就是脱离现实的
and self-respect without the reality.
虚假的自我效能与自我尊重
That's not self-esteem;
那些不是自尊
that's narcissism; that's detachment from reality.
那是自恋 脱离现实
And as we've been talking about constantly,
我们最近反复提到
psychological healthy is a function of connection to reality.
健康心理是要联系现实
So what is self-esteem? Self-esteem is founded in reality,
所以什么是自尊呢 自尊存在于现实中
in actual performance,in actual success,in actual practices.
存在于真实的行动 真实的成功 与真实的实践中
It is a product of hard work.
它是努力的产物
OK,do you remember the secret of success from 2 months ago?
好了 还记得2个月前我们讲到的成功的秘诀吗?
Optimism,belief in oneself,passion for what one is doing,
乐观 相信自己 对所做之事充满热情
and finally,hard work.
还有一点 努力奋斗
That's secret.
这就是秘诀
Again,someone,something we all know,
这些都是我们早就知道的
something that is commonsensical
都是基本常识
but again,common sense,in Voltaire's words,is not that common.
引用伏尔泰的话"常识不一定人皆有之"
Nathaniel Branden talks about 6 practices
Nathaniel Branden提出了培养自尊的
that are important for the cultivation of self-esteem:
6条重要实践
first,integrity.
首先 正直
That's your response paper this week
你们本周读书报告主题就是
to raise levels of awareness about integrity.
如何提高正直意识
And integrity means a match between what we say and what we do,
正直是指言行一致
the little things and the big things,
小事大事
whether it's "I'll be there at 5 minutes after 5",
无论是"我5点过5分到"
being there at 5 minutes after 5;
那就5点过5分到
saying that "I'm going to work out this week",
还是"我这周去健身"
and actually doing it.
那就要做到
Because you see,when we communicate,when we utter words,
因为我们沟通 说出每个词时
and we don't follow up on what we say,
如果言行不一致
what we are essentially communicating to ourselves:
那我们本质是在对自己说
what I say is not important; it doesn't matter.
我的话无关紧要 不重要
Whereas I maintain high levels of integrity,
反之 我保持高度正直
when I keep my words - again no one is perfect.
遵守诺言 当然没人是完美的
No one has perfect integrity as we'll talk about next time.
没人会是100%的正直 我们下次会讲到
But when I genuinely keep my word,
但是我真诚的遵守诺言
when I follow up on what I say,
言行一致
when I under-promise and over-deliver,
以低要求许诺 以高要求履诺
that's when I communicate to myself in action
就是以行动对自己说
remember,self-perception theory - in action,
还记得 自我知觉理论吗 通过行动
I communicate to myself,"My words matter; I matter."
我对自己说 "我的话很重要 我很重要"
So the practice of integrity.
所以要正直
The practice of self-awareness - know thyself.
要有自我察觉 了解你自己
Self-consciousness,as Branden talks about.
也就是Branden说的自我意识
Purposefulness,having goals,having self-concordant goals,
目的性 有目标 自我协调的目标
pursuing them,living a life of purpose,of calling,
努力追求 有目标有使命地生活
taking responsibility - remember once again no one is coming.
担起责任 记住 没人能帮你
It's up to you to make something of your lives.
只有靠你自己创造生活
The practice of self-acceptance.
要自我接纳
Permission to be human on a daily basis.
每天都要允许自己有人的天性
And finally,the practice of self-assertiveness:
最后 要有主见
to say no when it's appropriate;
该说不的时候说不
to say yes when that is appropriate;
该说是的时候说是
to stand up for what we believe in.
支持我们信仰的东西
These are the practices that over time cultivate self-esteem.
这些实践经年累月能培养我们的自尊
And they are also the product of self-esteem
它们也是自尊的产物
as we'll see next time,
我们下次会详细讲
it's a potential self-reinforcing loop.
这是个潜在的自我增强循环
So this is what self-esteem is.But there are more problems.
这就是自尊 但还有一些问题需要解答
There are more problems in self-esteem land.
自尊领域还有很多问题
Here is another important criticism.
还有一项重要的批评
You see,a lot of research shows that
很多研究表明
people with high self-esteem are more generous,
高自尊的人更慷慨
are more benevolent toward others.
对他人更博爱
They are generally good.They are nice.
总得来说他们都是好人
A lot research shows that.So that's wonderful,terrific.
许多研究都表明这点 这很棒 很好
However,
但是
there is also a lot of research that chose the exact opposite
还有很多研究结果恰恰相反
that people with high self-esteem display anti-social behavior,
高自尊的人表现出反社会行为
whether it's toward people they don't know,
无论是对不认识的人
especially toward people close to them.
尤其是对特别亲近的人
It's been associated with aggressive
它与攻击性不合作的行为
and uncooperative behavior.
有所关联
Levels of hostility associated with high self-esteem
一些研究显示敌意程度
in some studies.
也与高自尊有关
There are contradictory evidence - doesn't make sense.
这些证据自相矛盾 无法解释
What's going on in self-esteem land?
自尊到底是怎么回事
Hasn't been resolved until recently.
这个问题直到最近才弄清楚
Another criticism of self-esteem is what I mentioned,
对自尊的另一项批评 之前我提到过了
the paradox of self-esteem.
自尊的矛盾
You see,the praise that I received as a senior here
我在大四时 在哈佛求学期间
or as a student here in general was,
受到的表扬
the praise was based on reality.
基本上是基于事实的
You know I did well in squash - I got praise for that;
我壁球打得很好 得到了赞扬
I did well academically - I got praise for that.
学术成就优异 得到了表扬
So it was real; it was grounded in reality
所以都是真实的 基于现实的
and yet I still felt like I had low self-esteem.
但是我还是觉得自尊很低
In fact,the more praise I got,
事实上 我获得的赞扬越多
in many ways I felt the rock became heavier
越觉得石块越重
and  the mountain steeper.
山坡越陡
And that is not explained by traditional self-esteem research.
这点传统的自尊研究无法解释
Bednar and Peterson talk about,they talk about this paradox.
Bednar和Peterson谈到了这个矛盾
And they give examples in their book - this is the first place
他们在书中举了例子 这是我第一次看到
where I found someone talking about something
有人谈论
that I experienced for many years.
我这么多年的经历
They talked about the paradox where very often success
他们谈到了成功往往
is associated with low levels of self-esteem.
与低自尊共存的矛盾
So let me read to you an account of a client that they had
我读一段他们一位病人写的话
they are therapists - who has been very successful.
他俩都是心理医生 非常成功
And here he is,writing his journal:
他在日记中这样写道
"For the past several years,I felt that my life was meaningless.
"过去几年 我觉得生活毫无意义
This was an ironic state of affairs
这种状态非常讽刺
considering all I had accomplished.
因为我事业有成
Friends and relatives were always lauding me
亲朋好友总是赞美
for my good looks and intelligence.
我的外表与智慧
I was the first person on either side of my family
父母双方家中 我都是第一个
to graduate from college,
大学毕业生
doing so with honors.
而且是优秀荣誉毕业生
I had a good job with an important accounting firm.
我在大型会计事务所有一份好工作
I had plenty of dates.
不缺女伴
By all outward appearances,my life was very fulfilling.
表面看上去 我的生活非常满足
Yet I was miserable and felt increasingly depressed.
但我仍旧感到痛苦 日益沮丧
Six months of psychotherapy had helped me
6个月的心理疗法帮助我
to catch an occasional glimpse
瞥见了
of the underlying cause of my unhappiness.
我不快乐的潜在原因
It always seemed to involve low self-esteem
似乎与我的低自尊
or my disapproval of myself.
或自我否定有关
Somehow it seems like I really did have a low opinion of myself,
不知怎么 我似乎对自己评价很低
but I found that idea confusing,
这点让我很困惑
because of all the success in my life."
因为我生活很成功"
Bednar and Peterson talked,talk about,
Bednar与Peterson谈到了
or introduce there the paradox of self-esteem.
自尊的矛盾
That's what they call it.
这是他们的叫法
Self-esteem is not associated with success;
自尊与成功没有关系
it's not associated with social status,with money;
与社会地位 金钱没有关系
it's associated with other elements.
而是与其他因素有关
In fact,as the paradox shows very often,
事实上 这一矛盾经常显示
more success leads to more difficulty in this realm.
越成功遇到的困难越多
It was this difficulty that
我希望对这种困难进行研究
I wanted to explore and explored in my research.
并且的确进行了研究
And this is the formulation that I introduced.
这就是我之前谈到的公式
The first level of self-esteem was a dependent self-esteem,
第一层自尊 是依赖型自尊
because what I felt was that self-esteem was a construct,
因为我觉得自尊是一个构想
was not enough,was not enough.
这还不够
The contractions there were plenty;
还有各种矛盾
the paradox there was not explained by the notion of self-esteem.
还有自尊无法解释矛盾
So I divided self-esteem into three parts
所以我把自尊分为了三个部分
based on the work of Lovinger
根据Lovinger的理论
she did her work back in the 60s,based on the work of Maslow,
1960年代 她的研究是建立在Maslow
based on the work of Carl Rogers and Nathaniel Branden
Carl Rogers以及Nathaniel Branden理论的基础上的
who had talked about these things.
他们都谈到了这些问题
But again,we are not in the majority;
但是我们仍是小众
most people who talked about self-esteem talked about it
大多数人讲到自尊时
as a single construct.
仍把它当做独立的概念
The second component:
第二层自尊
self-esteem that is not contingent on others;
不取决于其他因素的自尊
and finally the third component essentially
第三层自尊 本质上
does not even need to be called self-esteem
甚至不必把它称为自尊
simply a sense of self.
而是一种自我感
Let me begin with each one,describing each one.
让我一个个来细说
And what I'll do in describing each one
我分析每层自尊时
is talk about the two components of self-esteem.
会从自尊的两个组成部分去讲
So essentially what I'll create is a three by two:
所以本质上是建立了一个2x3列联表
the three types of self-esteem,
三层自尊
each one - how it relates to worthiness,to self-respect;
每一层与价值感 或者说自我尊重的关系
and how it relates to competence
与能力的关系
the two components of Nathaniel Branden's work.
Nathaniel Branden理论里 自尊的两个组成部分
So first of all,
首先
in terms of worthiness - in terms of worthiness a person
从价值感方面来看
who has high dependent self-esteem is other determined.
高依赖型自尊的人 价值由他人决定
They enjoy and they need the appraisal.
他们喜欢 也需要别人的评估
If I do well in a lecture,
如果我讲座表现不错
and I get an external feedback that makes me great;
收到他人反馈让我感觉良好
if I don't get great feedback,I feel awful.
如果没得到正面反馈 我会感觉很糟糕
If I do well on an exams,
如果我考试表现优异
I get good feedback from my TF or parents,I feel terrific.
得到助教或家长肯定 就感觉棒极了
If someone tells me that they don't like something that I said,
如果有人说不喜欢我的某些言论
I feel awful.
我会感觉糟透了
My life is constantly affected by what other people think or say,
我的生活不断受到他人思想言论的影响
or what I think that they think,or what I think that they mean.
甚至是我以为他们怎么想 他们的意思
Constant evaluation - what do other people think of me?
不断的评估 其他人是怎么看我的
Like a looking glass -
仿佛他们是一面镜子
looking at other people as it reflects on me
仿佛从他们身上能看到镜中的自己一样
and taking their evaluation as the sense of self that I have.
把他们的评估当作自我感
People who have high dependent self-esteem are primarily,
高依赖型自尊的人主要
not only,
不是全部
but primarily motivated by what other people think and say.
但主要是由他人的想法言论驱动的
I will choose a job that will yield the most prestige,
我会从事高声望
the highest social status,
高社会地位的工作
that will yield the most accolades and praise.
能给我带来最多的赞赏与表扬
I will choose a partner
我选择伴侣
who I think most other people would approve of and like.
会选择受大多数人喜爱的人
Again,the sense of self - contingent on other people;
他们的自我感 取决于他人
then important decision are made
重要的决定
based on other people's approval or disapproval.
都是根据别人的赞同或不赞同而做出的
Second,sense of competence.
第二 能力感
The second component of self-esteem according to Branden
根据Branden理论 自尊的另一个组成部分
comes through other comparison.
来源于比较
How am I doing relative to other people?
跟其他人比 我表现怎么样
If I do better than others on the test,I feel great;
如果考试中 我比其他人考得好 我会感觉很好
if others do better than I do,
如果其他人考得比我好
no matter how objectively good or bad it is,
不管客观来说有多好或多差
what matters is how I am doing relative to others.
重要的是我跟其他人比表现怎么样
William James captured this.
William James抓住了这一点
He said,"I,who have staked my all in psychology,
他说 "我自以为掌握了心理学一切
am   when others know more psychology than I."
如果有人比我更了解心理学 我会感到被羞辱"
Compared to other people.
与他人比较
In fact most psychologists have talked about self-esteem
事实上 大多数心理学家都把自尊
as dependent self-esteem.
等同于依赖型自尊
The work of Cooley,talking about the looking glass metaphor;
Cooley在他的著作中谈到了镜子的比喻
the work of Mead's,back in 1934,
1934年Mead的著作
talking about dependent self-esteem
谈到了依赖型自尊
how we evaluate ourselves depends on what others say or think,
我们根据他人言论或看法来评估自己
or what we perceive they think or say about us.
或者我们认为他们对我们的看法或言论
Most of the thinkers have talked about it.
大多数思想家都谈到了这点
This is best captured;
这点形象地在童话中展示出来了
this is what I thought about for the first time in Fairy Tales.
我第一次上童话课时就想到了
This is best captured by the evil Queen:
白雪公主里的邪恶皇后生动的表现了这点
"Mirror,mirror on the wall,who is the fairest of them all?"
"魔镜魔镜告诉我 谁是世界上最美的女人"
And as long as the mirror says,
只要魔镜说
"You,my Queen,you are the fairest of them all," she feels great
"你 皇后陛下 你是世界上最美的女人" 她就觉得心满意足
As soon as there is one person who is more fair than thee,
一旦有人比她更漂亮
immediately she's mortified.
她就觉得蒙受奇耻大辱
The two components of self-esteem here:
说明了这种自尊的两个特点
first of all,the other determined.
首先 由他人决定
I'm asking a mirror to evaluate me,not self-determined.
我问镜子谁漂亮 而不是由我自己决定
So my worthiness comes from an external source.
所以我的价值感来源于外部
And second,competence - I compare myself to others.
第二 通过比较而获得能力感
Is there anyone who is fairer than I? Dependent self-esteem.
有人比我更美吗 依赖型自尊
Now I've quite literally now caricatured dependent self-esteem.
现在我似乎把依赖型自尊贬得一无是处
Let me make this very clear.
让我再说的清楚点
Everyone has some dependent self-esteem.
每个人都有依赖型自尊
There is no person that I've met or have heard of,
我从未遇见或听说任何人
who is oblivious to what other people think or say,
能完全不受他人想法言论
or to social comparisons.
或社会比较的的干扰
It's part of human nature.
这是人的天性的一部分
Nature to be commanded must be obeyed.
要支配天性 就必须服从天性
If we fight it,it will only intensify,
反抗天性 只会让其加剧
as we've seen numerous examples throughout this semester.
这学期我们已经看到过很多这方面的例子了
Permission to be human
允许自己有人的缺点
and part of being human is that we all have some dependent self...
依赖型自尊也是人性的一部分
The question is of degree.
问题在于程度
The important thing to understand about this model,
理解这个模型的一个关键是
these three levels is that it's an epigenetic model.
这三个层面是一个渐成模型
It is an epigenetic model.
渐成模型
And I've no idea what that means.No.
我也不知道这是什么意思
Epigenetic is that you first need to get past the first stage
渐成是指必须通过第一阶段
in order to get to the second stage;
才能到达第二阶段
you first need to get past the second stage
必须通过第二阶段
in order to get to the third stage;
才能到达第三阶段
that you cannot skip,for example,
不能越过某一级 比如
from stage 1 to stage 3 without going through 2.
从第一阶段直接到第三阶段 跳过了第二阶段
So everyone experiences dependent self-esteem always.
所以每个人都有依赖型自尊
However,after a time if we have a healthy dependence,
但是 如果我们有健康的依赖型自尊
which is natural,which we all have at an earlier age,
这很自然 我们小时候都经历过
later on it becomes independent.
一段时间后就会变成独立型自尊
And if we are able to cultivate a healthy independent self-esteem
如果我们能培养健康的独立型自尊
we go up to the unconditional self-esteem,
就能达到无条件自尊
to the state of inter-dependence,which is the highest level.
达到互相依赖型 也就是最高层次
But even at the highest level,we still have reminisce.
但是即使在最高层次 其他两种还是存在的
And we will always have elements of the dependent
我们会一直拥有依赖型
as well as the independent sense of self.
及独立型自我感
When I started doing my research initially,
研究一开始时
I said,I depicted independent versus dependent
我想把独立型与依赖型对比
I hadn't thought of unconditional at the time
我当时还没有想到无条件型
as independent good,dependent bad.
想当然地认为独立型好 依赖型坏
And I tried to get rid of the dependent self.
我试图摆脱依赖型自我
And what happened - it just simply intensified.
结果它反而强化了
It simply got stronger.
变得更强烈
And I became even more dependent;
我变得更加依赖
whereas as soon as I started to accept it
然而 一旦我开始接受它
remember,I talked about it,permission to be human
记住吗 我说过 允许自己有人的天性
as soon as I accepted it as part of human nature,
一旦我接受它为人性的一部分
it actually lost much of its power over me.
对我的影响反而小多了
Still there as it is for everyone,but the question is of degree.
人人都有依赖型自尊 只是程度不同
The second level self-esteem,independent self-esteem.
第二个层面是独立型自尊
As its name suggests,
顾名思义
that self-esteem - that's not contingent on other people.
这种自尊不取决于他人
So in terms of worthiness,
在价值感方面
I evaluate myself according to my own standards.
我用自己的标准评估自己
I'm self-determined.
自我决定
I determine how good a book that I wrote is.
我自己评定写的书好不好
Ultimately - the ultimate arbiter: I do take into consideration
最终的公断人是我自己 但我会参考
and listen to what other people are saying;
和听取其他人的意见
but at the end of the day I'm the one who decides.
但是最终还是由我自己说了算
Competence,not comparison to others but comparison to oneself.
在能力感方面 不与别人比较 而是与自己比较
Have I improved? Am I better writer today than I was in the past?
我进步了吗 是不是比过去写得好了?
Do I know more math today than I knew
我的数学是不是比
at the beginning of the semester?
学期初进步了
Am I able to apply more things from positive psychology
我是不是比一开始能运用更多的
than I applied initially?
积极心理学知识了?
Not compared to my roommate
不与室友比较
who is applying so much more or so much less,
无论他懂的比我多还是少
but mostly focused on the self.
我只关注自己
Once again,people who wrote about this type of self-esteem:
很多人都提到了这种自尊
Nathaniel Branden,Abraham Maslow,Carl Rogers,
Nathaniel Branden  Abraham Maslow与Carl Rogers
and a handful of others.
还有其他很多人
A person who has dependent self-esteem
有依赖型自尊的人
looks for constant approval,
需要不断寻求他人肯定
is afraid of criticism,
害怕批评
very often is associated with perfectionism;
经常与完美主义相连
whereas the person has independent sense of self
而拥有独立型自我感的人
looks for criticism.
寻求批评
In fact that person constantly looks for "beautiful enemies",
这样的人其实不断寻找"美丽的敌人"
people who will challenge him or her,
那些挑战他
who will help them in their apprenticeship to the truth.
帮助他寻找真相的人
Because they want to improve.
因为他们想要进步
Their motivation,their primary motivation is
他们的动力 主要动力
"What am I passionate about?" "What do I care about?"
是"我热爱什么?" "我喜欢什么?"
"What do I really,really want to do with my life?"
"我真正想做的是什么"
They are about pursuing self-concordant goals.
他们想追求自我调节的目标
A friend of mine,Maltimore Devano,
我的一个朋友Maltimore Devano
philosopher writes about dependent self-esteem.
他是一位哲学家 写到自尊时曾说
He says this person answers or is associated with following:
他是这么说有依整型自尊的人
we say that we want the truth,
我们说 想寻找真相
what do we mean is that we want to be correct.
真正的意思是 我们希望自己是正确的
We say that we want the truth,
我们说 想寻找真相
what do we mean is that we want to be correct.
真正的意思是 我们希望自己是正确的
Many people with dependent self-esteem say,
许多依赖型自尊的人说
"Yes,I'm really pursuing what is right,
"是的 我正在追求真理
what is true,what is noble",
追求高尚"
whereas actually the motivation
但是实际上我们的动机
is protecting the self from criticism,from negative evaluation,
是为了保护自己免受批评 免受负面评价
from a lower sense of self-esteem that is contingent on others.
避免这种依赖他人的自尊变得更低
And once again,in contrast to saying we want the truth
所以 不同于那些说想寻求真相
meaning we want to be correct,
其实只希望自己是正确的的人
we have the person with independent self-esteem
拥有独立型自尊的人
who wants beautiful enemies,
想寻找美丽的敌人
who really is an apprentice to the truth.
他们才是正真追寻真相
To summarize,initially the first two by two:
总结一下 最初的2x2表
dependent self-esteem - worthiness,determined by others.
依赖型自尊 价值感由他人决定
I do things for accolades,for praise primarily.
我做一切主要是为了赞赏 表演
And competence - how well I am doing relative to other people;
能力感 与他人相比我做得怎么样
am I better or worse than them?
比他们好还是差
And that determines my self-esteem.
这决定了我的自尊
In terms of my worthiness,in terms of independent self-esteem,
而独立型自尊的价值感和能力感是
I compare myself to myself - have I improved;
拿自己跟自己比罗 我进步了吗
am I getting better; am I learning?
改进了吗 学到新东西了吗?
And my worthiness is determined by my own evaluation.
我的价值感是由我自己的评估决定
Third level,unconditional self-esteem.
第三个层次 无条件自尊
In many ways,this is not even self-esteem.
从多个角度看 这甚至不算是自尊
Because there is no esteeming involved here.
因为其中没有涉及自尊
The first component,worthiness,not contingent
第一部分 价值感
it's not contingent on other people's evaluations;
不取决于他人评价
it's not even contingent on my evaluation.
也不取决于自我评价
I'm confident enough not to be engaged in evaluations.
我有充分的自信 不参与任何评价
In terms of competence,it's interdependent.
其次是能力感 互相依赖
I don't compare myself to how well I am doing relative to others,
不把自己与他人比较
nor even how well I'm doing relative to myself.
也不与自己比较
I am in a state of being.
我处于某种状态
Interdependence with others - fully comfortable in my own skin.
与他人互相依赖 同时又怡然自得
For example,
比如
a person writing a book who has high dependent self-esteem
一个高依赖型自尊的人写书
is primarily motivated by the accolades,
他的动力主要是将要获得的
by the praise she or he will get;
赞赏和表扬
a person who has high dependent,or,
高依赖型自尊的人
and also by how well that book is doing relative to other books;
还会把他的书与其他人的比较
a person with independent self-esteem writes a book
高独立型人格的人写书
and derives pleasure and satisfaction from writing better
他的快乐与满足的来源是
than he or she did in the past,from improving,
通过改进写得比过去好了
as well as from self-evaluation of the book: this is good.
还有对书的自我评价 这本书写得真好
A person who has unconditional self-esteem simply writes a book.
而无条件型自尊的人只是写书
Why? Because he or she once,
为什么? 因为一旦他们
if they have a good idea,a good book to be out there,
有灵感 就会写出一本好书
they derive as much satisfaction,
他们从他人的好书中
as much pleasure when they see another person's book,who is good
也能获得同样的满足与乐趣
They are interdependent.
他们互相依靠
They see themselves as one with others.
他们视自己为团体一员
Once again,everyone has some components of dependence,
所有人都有一定程度的依赖型自尊
some components of independence,
一定程度的独立型自尊
and some components of unconditional self-esteem.
以及一定程度的无条件自尊
The question is of degree.The model is epigenetic.
问题在于程度 模型是渐成型的
It takes a lifetime very often
通常需要一辈子时间
to cultivate more and more of the unconditional self.
把无条件自我培养得越来越强
Now one of the criticism is that I face
我和其他赞同无条件自尊的学者
and other writes who have written about unconditional self-esteem
受到的批评之一是
is that to be at this stage of "Well,I don't really care or
要达到这种状态 "我不在乎
don't care that much about whether I get criticism or evaluation"
不是很在乎我受到批评还是评价"
is that one becomes detached from others,that one does not care.
就会变得与他人脱离了 对什么都不在乎
But that is not the case.
但情况不是这样
You see,
瞧
there are many parallels between unconditional self-esteem
无条件自尊与佛教的超然
and the Buddhist conception of detachment.
有许多相似处
Let me read to you something.
我给你们读一段
This was written by the Buddhist nun,Thubten Chodron,
图丹却准法师的语录
and I quote: "Ordinarily,
"通常
we become very upset when we are criticized or insulted.
我们受到批评或侮辱时 会变得非常不安
We are angry when our possessions are stolen;
我们财产被偷时 会变得异常愤怒
we are jealous if someone else gets the promotion we wanted;
如果期望已久的升职被别人抢去 我们会嫉妒
we are proud of our looks or athletic ability.
我们以自己的外表体能为荣
By contrast,when we reach the state of detachment,
相比之下 当我们达到了超然的境界
our mind becomes clearer
我们的头脑变得更明晰
and more capable of enjoying things for what they are.
懂的享受事物的原本
We live more in the present,appreciating things as they are now,
我们懂得把握现在 欣赏事物的原本
without fantasies about what they are or will be.
不再对它们有诸多幻想
We become less ego-sensitive
我们对别人的一举一动
to every action other people do in relation to us."
不再那么敏感"
Now at the same time,detachment or unconditional self-esteem
同时 超然或无条件自尊
which is the parallel that I'm drawing,
我正比较两者的相似点
does not mean being indifferent
它们并不意味着冷漠
or rejecting other people's feelings.
回避他人情感
She continues,"On the contrary,when we are not attached,
她继续说"相反地 当我们超然后
our relationships with others are harmonious,
我们与他人的关系变得更和谐
and in fact,we care more about them.
事实上 我们更关心他们了
We become more compassionate,more empathetic toward others."
变得更有同情心 更同情他人"
Detachment or unconditional self-esteem simply means that
超然或无条件自尊只是指
we are distancing ourselves
我们让自己远离
or not experiencing as much feelings of jealousy,
羡慕嫉妒
feelings of envy,constant superiority or inferiority,
高傲自卑
ongoing comparison to others.
与他人对比的情绪
It means,on many levels,that we are one with them.
我们和他们融为一体
This is what the research shows.
这就是研究结果
You know,in fact,you can think about
事实上 你可以把无条件自尊
unconditional self-esteem as parallel to going to a movie.
比作看电影
When you are going to a movie,what happens?
你去电影院 然后呢
You are empathizing with the characters there.
你与角色产生了共鸣
When they go through a hard time,
当他们经历艰难困苦时
you experience a hard time viscerally;
你在心里也经历了一回
when they thrive and succeed,you thrive and succeed.
当他们获得成功时 你也觉得获得了成功
You are one with them.
你和他们融为了一体
Why? Because your ego is not threatened
为什么? 因为你的自我不受威胁
you are not threatened by their success;
他们的成功没有威胁到你
their good looks are not threatening to you;
他们的美貌没有威胁到你
their successes are not a threat to you.
他们的成功对你来说不是威胁
Why? Because it's just a movie.
为什么? 因为这只是电影
Now imagine: if we could have these emotions,
想象一下 如果我们能有这种情感
feelings with as opposed to against,
感受而不是对立
imagine we could have these emotions in real life,
想象在真实生活中拥有这些情感
how much more powerful would they be?
这样的人会有多强大?
This is the experience,again of a movie,
这是电影的经历
but so much more powerful because it's real
但对拥有高无条件自尊的人来说
of a person who has high levels of unconditional self-esteem.
会有多强大
Cultivating self-esteem,unconditional self-esteem takes time.
培养自尊 无条件自尊需要时间
It's a lifelong process.
这是一生的过程
In many ways,it's parallel to learning how to walk.
类似学走路
What happens when we learn how to walk? Initially we can't.
我们学走路是什么样的 一开始我们不会
After a while we are able to get up,but we need some help;
一段时间后 我们会站起来 但需要帮助
we are dependent on a chair,on our parent to hold us,
我们依靠椅子 父母支撑我们
dependent on other people.
依靠其他人
Next level - after a while,is independent.
下一阶段 又过了一段时间 我们独立了
We are able to walk by ourselves.
能够自己走了
But we walk still by thinking about picking up this foot
但走的时候仍旧要想着抬脚
and we are precarious.
而且觉得不安全
We are uncertain,but we are independent.
但我们是独立的
Later on we simply and naturally walk.
渐渐地 我们会自然的走了
We don't need to think about it constantly.
不用再想着抬脚
When it comes to a sense of self,
自我感与之相似
initially there is no sense of self when we are born.
我们刚出生时 没有自我感
After a while,the sense of self is dependent on other people,
一段时间后 自我感依赖于其他人
other people's evaluation.
其他人的评价
Then,after a while,
然后 过了一段时间
we become independent of what other people say,
我们变得独立 不受他人影响
or we try to assert our independence,
试图坚持主见
but we are constantly evaluating ourselves,
但是我们不断的评估自己
constantly comparing ourselves.
比较自己
And then finally,after a while,
最后 又过了一段时间
when we cultivate the strong sense of independence,
我们培养出来强烈的独立感
we simply and naturally exist.
自然存在了
That is if nature is allowed to take its course.
这要顺其自然
And that takes time.
而这需要时间
David Schnarch talks about the average person at the age of 50
David Schnarch谈到普通人到了50岁
becoming known rather than validated
懂得被了解而不是被认可
strong unconditional self-esteem.
这就是强烈的无条件自尊
Maslow talks about the self-actualized person
Maslow认为人到了45或50岁
at the age of 45 or 50.
才能自我实现
That's unconditional self-esteem.
这就是无条件型自尊
It takes time; it's epigenetic.
这需要时间 它是渐成的
But the process itself,as we improve and grow,
但我们改进成长的这一过程
is or can be as enjoyable,
是可以很愉悦的
as pleasurable as learning how to walk.
就像学走路一样充满乐趣
I'll see you next week.
我们下周见